Much of the remainder of this section of the
course will cover lists and list management.
A list is a set of multiple values assigned
to a single variable.
Lists have square brackets surrounding the
values within the list.
Later in this section, we will cover different
types of lists and their uses, but in this
topic, we will cover indexing, which is the
positioning of each element within a list.
Take this 122-indexing file, for example.
Here, line 1 lists categories related to Ancient
Near East history eras.
If this code is to be part of a quiz-based
game, people using the app will need to choose
a category at any given time.
Line 2 has a print statement to print the
categories variable.
Let’s run this code and see the result.
The result is that we see all the categories.
But what if we just want to see one category?
I will copy the code on line 2 and paste it
on line 4.
Then, I will add a 1 inside square brackets
inside the closing parenthesis to indicate
I want to print just the first category, the
Early Bronze Age.
I will run the code, and we see that what
we wanted did not print.
The Middle Bronze Age printed instead.
Why is that?
To understand why, we need to understand a
basic programming concept about indexes and
similar list-based situations.
Most programming languages, including Python,
are zero-based with lists and their values.
By zero-based, we mean that the first value
in the list is at index zero, the next one
is index one, and so forth.
Thus, to return the first item in the list,
this number for the index needs to be zero.
I will make that change, rerun the code, and
now we will see our desired Early Bronze Age
value.
To further demonstrate the zero-based point,
I will change the number for the category
to 2, rerun the code, and Late Bronze Age,
the third item in the list, is returned.
One aspect of indexing that causes consternation
for some is trying to figure out how to return
the last or maybe second-to-last item in the
list.
If this list had 20 items or so, one would
need to count the number of items in the list
to return the correct item at or near the
end of the list, which is a cumbersome process
and can lead to inaccuracies in obtaining
the correct indexed value from a list.
However, Python can easily obtain the last
item in the list by returning an index of
negative one, as I will do here on line 4,
and then rerunning the code.
And we see the last element in the list.
What do you think will happen if I change
this index to -2?
Upon running this code, we see the second-to-last
item in the list.